The Solar system. Our home in space.
We live in a peaceful
part of the Milky Way.
Our home is the Solar system,
a 4.5-billion-year-old formation that
races around the galactic centre at
200,000 km/h and circles it
once every 250 million years.
Our star, the Sun, is at the centre
of the Solar system.
It’s orbited by eight planets,
trillions of asteroids and comets and a
few dwarf planets.
The eight planets. Divided into four
planets like ours:
Mercury, Venus, Earth and Mars,
and four gas giants:
Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune.
Mercury is the smallest and
lightest of all the planets.
A Mercury year is shorter than the Mercury
day, which leads to
enormous fluctuations in temperature.
Mercury does not have an
atmosphere or a moon.
Venus is one of the brightest objects in
the Solar system and by far
the hottest planet, with atmospheric
pressure that is
92 times higher than on Earth.
An out-of-control greenhouse effect
means that Venus never
cools below 437 °C.
Venus also doesn’t have a moon.
Earth is our home and the only planet
with temperatures that are moderate enough
to allow for a surplus of liquid water.
Furthermore, it’s so far the only place
where life is known to exist.
The Earth has one moon.
Mars is the second smallest planet
in the Solar system
and hardly massive enough to keep a very
thin atmosphere.
Its Olympus Mons is the largest
mountain in the Solar system,
more than three times as high as Mount
Everest.
Mars has two small moons.
Jupiter is the largest and most massive
planet in the Solar system.
It consists largely of hydrogen and
helium
and is the theatre for the largest and
most powerful storms we know.
Its largest storm, the Great Red Spot,
is three times as large as Earth.
Jupiter has sixty-seven moons.
Saturn is the second largest planet and
possesses the smallest density
of all the planets.
If you had a sufficiently large bathtub,
Saturn would swim in it.
Saturn is also known for its extended,
very visible ring system.
It has sixty-two moons.
Uranus is the third largest planet
and one of the coldest.
Of all the gas giants, it’s also
the smallest.
The special thing about Uranus is that
its axis of rotation
is tilted sideways in contrast to the
seven other planets.
It has twenty-seven moons.
Neptune is the last planet in the Solar
system and is similar to Uranus.
It’s so far removed from the Sun that
a Neptune year is 164 Earth years long.
The highest wind speed ever measured
was in a storm on Neptune,
at just under 2,100 km/h.
Neptune has fourteen moons.
If we compare the sizes of the planets,
the differences between them
become even clearer.
Jupiter is the leader in terms of
size and weight;
small Mercury, on the other hand,
is even smaller than one of Jupiter’s
moons, Ganymede.
Jupiter is so massive that alone it
contains roughly 70% of the mass
of all the other planets and has a massive
impact on its surroundings.
That’s a blessing for Earth, since
Jupiter draws most of
the dangerously large asteroids
that could wipe out life on Earth.
But even Jupiter is a dwarf in
comparison to our star, the Sun.
Calling it massive does not do
justice to the Sun.
It makes up 99.86% of the mass
in our Solar system.
For the most part, it consists of
hydrogen and helium.
Only less than 2% is made up of
heavy elements, like oxygen or iron.
At its core, the Sun fuses 620 million
tons of hydrogen each second
and generates enough energy to satisfy
mankind’s needs for years.
But not only the eight planets
orbit our Sun.
Trillions of asteroids and comets
also circle it.
Most of them are concentrated into
two belts:
the asteroid belt between Mars and
Jupiter
and the Kuiper belt at the edge of the
Solar system.
These belts are home to countless
objects, some as large as a dust particle,
others the size of dwarf planets.
The most well-known object in the
asteroid belt is Ceres;
the most well-known objects in the Kuiper
belt are Pluto, Makemake and Haumea.
Usually we describe the asteroid belt as
a dense collection of bodies that
constantly collide.
But in fact, the asteroids are
distributed across an area that is
so indescribably large that it’s even
difficult to see two asteroids at once.
Despite the billions of objects in them,
the asteroid belts are fairly empty
places.
And nonetheless, there are collisions
over and over again.
The mass of both belts is also
unimpressive:
the asteroid belt has a little less than
4% of our Moon’s mass, and
the Kuiper belt is only between one 25th
and one 10th of Earth’s mass.
One day, the Solar system will cease to
exist.
The Sun will die, and Mercury, Venus and
maybe Earth too will be destroyed.
In 500 million years it will become hotter
and hotter until at some point
it will melt Earth’s crust.
Then the Sun will grow and grow and
either swallow Earth
or at least turn it into a sea of lava.
When it has burnt up all its fuel and
lost most of its mass,
it will shrink to a white dwarf and burn
gently for a few billion more years
before it goes out entirely.
Then, at the latest, life in the Solar
system will no longer be possible.
The Milky Way will not even notice it.
A small part of it in one of its arms
will become just a tiny bit darker.
And mankind will cease to exist
or leave the Solar system
in search of a new home.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community